Guide to the Elizabeth Ransom Photograph Collection 1891-1892 PR 237
New-York Historical Society
Elizabeth Ransom Photograph Collection
1891-1892
New-York Historical Society
PR 237
0.83 Linear feet (61 glass negatives and 3 albumen prints)
The collection contains 61 glass negatives of buildings, parks, events and potraits in New York City and state. Also included are three albumen prints of the steamboat Harlem and an unidentified residence. The Elizabeth Ransom Collection is digitized and available in the Shelby White and Leon Levy Digital Library.
Provenance
Gift of Elizabeth Ransom.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Biographical Note
The collection was donated by Elizabeth Ransom, but other than her name, we know nothing else about her or her connection to the negatives. Each negative has a number, given by the New-York Historical Society and a description. The photographer is unidentified.
Scope and Content Note
The Elizabeth Ransom Photograph Collection contains mainly glass negatives taken from 1891-1892. The majority are New York City images and include buildings, parks, street scenes and events. The collection is divided into two series: Glass Negatives and Photographs.
Arrangement
Material is divided into two series: I. Glass Negatives; II. Photographs. The negatives have been further arranged by subject, with images of New York City broken into smaller categories.
Related Material at the Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections
Other photographs of New York in the late 1800's can be found in the Geographic File (PR 020), the Robert L. Bracklow Photograph Collection (PR 008) and the George P. Hall & Sons Photograph Collection (PR 024).
Existence and Location of Copies
Digital copies are available in the Shelby White and Leon Levy Digital Library.
Glass negatives.; Albumen prints.; Bryant Park (New York, N.Y.); Fifth Avenue (New York, N.Y.); Central Park (New York, N.Y.); Parades -- New York (State) -- New York.; Portraits.; Photographic prints.; New York (N.Y.) -- Buildings, structures, etc.; New York (N.Y.) -- Pictorial works.; Ketchum, George; Moore, Ada; Voorhees, May
- Series I: Glass Negatives
  Scope and Contents note
  Series I. Glass Negatives is comprised of 61 negatives. These negatives have been arranged by subject, with images of New York City broken into smaller categories.
  Images of Hempstead, New York include a July 4th parade. Photographs of fire engines as well as the Hook and Ladder, Hose and Steamer Company's house on Fulton Street are included.
  Images of New York City are divided into the following subjects:
  Buildings contains images of All Souls, St. Bartholomew and St. Thomas Churches, the Metropolitan Museum of Art, Columbia College and Wilson & Kellogg's School.
  Central Park has images of various buildings, monuments and locations in the park. There are several photographs of the menagerie; most are of various animals in their cages.
  Parades and Processions include the Saint Patrick's Parade, as well as the funeral procession of General William T. Sherman. These images were taken from inside Wilson & Kellogg's School.
  Residences contains images of the Havemeyer residence on Fifth Avenue and 66th Street, a shanty on Madison Avenue and 77th where Blind Tom Foley and his family once lived, the Tiffany House on Madison Avenue and 72nd Street, the Vanderbilt twin houses at 640 Fifth Avenue, Cornelius Vanderbilt II residence on Fifth Avenue and 57th Street, and William K. Vanderbilt's home on Fifth Avenue and 52nd Street.
  Miscellaneous images include the reservoir at Bryant Park, an advertising fence on Fifth Avenue advertising Barnum & Bailey's Circus, and a F.D.N.Y. fire engine.
  Portraits included in this collection are informal. Most were taken outside, near an unidentified house in Hempstead, NY. While the sitters are usually identified there are several with only a first name listed. Portraits include the following identified sitters: Christopher Greer, George Ketchum, Ada Moore, Nellie Moore, Angie Voorhees, and May Voorhees.
  - HEMPSTEAD, N.Y.
    - Fire engines on Parade, 1891 July 4 (Box 1, Folder unknown container)
  - NEW YORK, N.Y.
    - Buildings, 1891 (Box 1, Folder unknown container)
    - Central Park, 1891 (Box 1, Folder unknown container)
    - Central Park - Menagerie, 1891 April (Box 1, Folder unknown container)
    - Parades & Processions, 1891 (Box 2, Folder unknown container)
    - Residences, 1891 (Box 2, Folder unknown container)
    - Miscellaneous, 1891 (Box 2, Folder unknown container)
  - PORTRAITS
    - Miscellaneous, 1891-1892 (Box 2, Folder unknown container)
- Series II: Photographs
  Series II. Photographs contains three albumen prints, mounted on board. Two images are of the steamboat Harlem. The other photograph shows an unidentified house.
  - Miscellaneous, [1891] (Box 2, Folder 1)